A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Education, 2001-2010 (bulk 2005-2009)
Library of Virginia
- III. Office of the Secretary, 2001-2009 (bulk 2006-2009)., Extent: 9.96 cubic feet (22 boxes). (Box 15-35; 53)
  - Subseries III.D. Files of Jean Bankos, Senior Advisor to the Governor for Educational Projects, 2001-2002; 2004-2009 (bulk 2006-2009)., Extent: 3.35 cubic feet (4 boxes).
    - Briefing and Meeting Binders
      - Virginia Board of Education, Committees, 2006-2007
        - Standards of Quality Committee, 2006 October 24. (Box 25, Folder 14)
      - Southern Governors' Association, Education in the South: A Passport to Opportunity, Communications Plan and Action Toolkit, 2007. (Box 25, Folder 15)
      - Virginia Board of Education's Literacy Policy Summit, Closing the Achievement Gap: A Focus on Adolescent Literacy, 2007 May 1. (Box 25, Folder 16)
      - National Association of System Heads (NASH), State Teams P-16 Summer Institute, Minneapolis, Minnesota (Judy Heiman's), 2007 July 29-31. (Box 25, Folder 17)
      - CollegeBoard, Connecting All Students to College Success and Opportunity, Virginia Governor's P-16 Council Meeting, 2006 September 13. (Box 25, Folder 18)
      - CollegeBoard, State Reports for Virginia, 2007 August (1 of 2). (Box 25, Folder 19)
      - CollegeBoard, State Reports for Virginia, 2007 August (2 of 2). (Box 25, Folder 20)
      - Changing the Course of Science Education, 2007 National Leadership Development and Strategic Planning Symposium on K-16 Science Education for State Teams, Washington, D.C., 2007 September 30-2007 October 2. (Box 26, Folder 1)
      - Parent meeting with the Governor's Office concerning the proposed revision to the Regulations Governing Special Education Programs for Children with Disabilities in Virginia, 2008 March 4. (Box 26, Folder 2)
      - Women Education Leaders in Virginia, Learning and Leading in the 21st Century, Charlottesville, Virginia, 2008 April 3-4. (Box 26, Folder 3)
      - Virginia's Community College, Hire Education 2008 Workforce Development Conference, 2008 December 9-12. (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Grant Proposals for a Governor's Career and Technical Academy (1 of 3), 2007. (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Grant Proposals for a Governor's Career and Technical Academy (2 of 3), 2007. (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Grant Proposals for a Governor's Career and Technical Academy (3 of 3), 2007. (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - The JASON Project, 2008. (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Early Childhood Alignment Project, 2006. (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - 2008-2010 FY Education Budget, 2007-2008. (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - National Governors Association (NGA) STEM Center Grant Program
      - Correspondence, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 11)
      - Innovation America Initiative, 2006. (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - Grant Documents, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Development and Implementation of a Public Communication Campaign to Promote Educational Attainment, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Teacher Quality, 2002; 2004; 2007. (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Teacher Induction; Teaching Standards, 2006-2007. (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Commission on Youth, Study of Truancy and School Dropout Prevention Advisory Group
      - Dropout Subcommittee Meeting, 2008 October 8. (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - Meeting, 2008 October 14. (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - Meeting, 2009 April 20. (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - Meeting, 2009 May 29. (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - Meeting, 2009 June 15. (Box 26, Folder 18)
      - Improving School Attendance, A Resource Guide for Virginia Schools, 2005 August. (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Private School Regulations, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Public School Forum of North Carolina, 2006. (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - National Governors Association, Virginia's Ten-Year Goals, 2008. (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Career Coach, 2006; 2008. (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Virginia Civil Rights Memorial, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - Governor's School Program, 2007. (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Career Readiness Certificate, 2008. (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Advanced Placement (AP), 2008-2009. (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Autism Study by Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC), 2008. (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Governor's VIP Award, 2009 February 16. (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Virginia STAR Program, 2008. (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Special Education Regulations, 2008. (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Flexbooks/Open Source, 2008. (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Commission on Civics Education, 2005-2007. (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Commission on Civics Education, 2007-2008. (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Standards of Accreditation, 2008-2009. (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - National Board Certified Teachers in Virginia, 2006-2008. (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Achievable Dream Academy, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Alignment Project, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Early Learning, July 2006. (Box 27, Folder 4a)
    - Teacher Evaluation Report, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Stanford English Language Proficiency (SELP) Issue, 2006 November 3. (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Licensure Regulations Governor Early/Primary Education, Elementary Education and Middle Education, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - No Child Left Behind (NCLB) Reauthorization, 2007 February. (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Queen's Visit, 2007 May 3. (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Virginia Preschool Initiative (VPI), 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Career Education Foundation (VCEF), 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Great Virginia Teach-In, 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Secretary of Education Legislative Studies, 2004-2005. (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Town Hall/Regulations, 2005; undated. (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - 2006-2007 Teacher Salary Survey Report, 2006 December 1. (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Blueprint for Virginia Public Schools: A Long-Range Plan for the Future of Public Education in Virginia, 2001. (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - 2006 Commonwealth Education Poll, Public Opinion in Virginia on Schools and Education, 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Virginia Department of Education Briefing, Reading First, 2008 January. (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Virginia Department of Correctional Education, 2008. (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Adult Education, 2008. (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - 2006 Legislative Proposals, 2005. (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Budget Meetings, 2007. (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - United States Department of Education Correspondence, re: Limited English Proficient (LEP), 2007. (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - No Child Left Behind (NCLB) Reauthorization Background, 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Background on Limited English Proficient (LEP) issues with United States Department of Education, 2007. (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Congressional Delegation Follow Up, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Department of Education, Commission on Civics Education Interim Report, 2007 November 1. (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Department of Education, Special Education Briefing Report, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Dual Enrollment, 2005-2006. (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Governor's Performance Leadership Forum, 2006 April 27-28. (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Governor Kaine's Workforce Development Strategic Plan, 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - Economic Development Strategic Plan, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Standards of Quality (SOQ) Review, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - NASA Partnership, 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - STEM Subcommittee (HJR 25), 2006. (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Virginia Association of School Superintendents (VASS), 2006. (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Virginia Association of Secondary School Principals (VASSP), 2007 January. (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Weekly Report Guidelines, 2006. (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - State Strong Council, Finance, 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - Barbara Gault, Price of Pre-K, 2006-2007. (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - Health Virginians/Healthy Students Obesity Summit (NGA Grant), 2007. (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Virginia's National Governors Association Honor States Grant to Redesign the American High School, 2008. (Box 27, Folder 24)
    - Virginia's National Governors Association Honor States Grant to Redesign the American High School, Presentations, 2005-2007. (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - National Governors Association, Virginia's Honor States Ten-Year Goals, 2006-2007. (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Virginia's National Governors Association Honor States Grant to Redesign the American High School, Gates Foundation, 2006-2007. (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - P-16 Readiness Work Group, 2006-2007. (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Virginia's P-16 Education Council, Longitudinal Data Systems Work Group, 2006-2007. (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Virginia's P-16 Education Council, Policy Forum, 2006-2007. (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Standards of Accreditation (SOA), 2006-2008. (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Subseries III.F. Files of Kendall Tyree, Special Assistant to the Secretary of Education, 2002; 2005-2007., Extent: 0.53 cubic feet (2 boxes).
    This subseries is housed in two boxes and is arranged chronologically and by subject files. Kendall Tyree served as Special Assistant to the Secretary of Education from June 2005 to October 2008.
    Includes: CVC Campaign, Commission on Civics Education, Commission on Youth, Governor's Advisory Workgoup on K-12 Education, General Assembly session bill tracking, Queen Elizabeth II's visit to Virginia in 2007, American Sesquicentennial of the American Civil War Commission, and career technical training.
    - Governor's Advisory Workgroup, K-12 Education, 2002; 2005. (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Latino Advisory Board, 2006 April 4. (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Literary Fund Forecast, 2006 December 12. (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Taiwan-United States Sister Relations Alliance, 2007 February 3. (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - 2007 General Assembly Session Bill Tracking, 2007 January-February. (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Career Technical Education, 2007. (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Pre-K Pilot Discussion Session, 2007 April 23. (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Virginia Israel Advisory Board Meeting, 2007 June 28. (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Council on Virginia's Future, Educational Attainment Discussion, 2007 October 22. (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - Subject Files
      - CVC Campaign, 2005-2007. (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - Virginia Commission on Civics Education, 2006. (Box 35, Folder 2)
      - Virginia Commission on Youth, 2005-2006. (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - Legislative Action Summaries, 2005-2006. (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - Queen Elizabeth II Visit to Capitol Square,(student lists and logistics) 2007. (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - Reappropriation Plan for 2006 Fiscal Year Expenditure, 2006 September 18. (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - Virginia Sesquicentennial of the American Civil War Commission, 2007. (Box 35, Folder 7)
- IV. Weekly Report Files, 2006-2009., Extent: 0.35 cubic feet (1 box). (Box 36)
  The Weekly Report Files series is housed in one box, arranged chronologically and contains the weekly reports submitted to the Governor and Chief of Staff by the Secretary of Education. Reports were submitted each Thursday and placed in a binder for the Governor that he took with him at the end of the day on Friday. A second copy of the report was made for the Chief of Staff. Each report contains information on legislation, Governor's initiatives/special projects, agency matters/operations, events/agency visits, audits/investigations/compliance, stakeholder issues and pending decisions. This series provides a weekly account of the issues and policy decisions of the Secretary of Education during the Kaine administration.
  Governor Kaine's copy of the Secretary of Education's reports has been digitized. It is part of the Timothy M. Kaine Administration (2006-2010) Cabinet Weekly Reports collection.
  - 2006 (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - 2007 (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - 2008 (Box 36, Folder 3)
  - 2009 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - SWAM Weekly Reports, 2009. (Box 36, Folder 5)
- V. Decision Briefs: Supporting Documentation, 2008-2010., Extent: 0.35 cubic feet (1 box). (Box 37)
  The Decision Briefs series is housed in one box and is arranged chronologically. This series consists of supporting documentation from assigned state agencies asking the Secretary's permission to perform a major function, policy initiative, or expenditure. This series includes briefs, memoranda, and correspondence.
  Secretary of Education decision briefs from 2006 and 2007 can be found in the Records of the Policy Office, Governor Timothy M. Kaine, 2003-2010 (bulk 2006-2009), Accession 44690 and 44701, State Records Collection, Library of Virginia (series I).
  - 2010 January-2009 October (Box 37, Folder 1)
  - 2009 October-2009 July (Box 37, Folder 2)
  - 2009 May-2009 January (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - 2008 December-2008 March (Box 37, Folder 4)
  - 2006-2008 (Miscellaneous) (Box 37, Folder 5)
- VI. Public Relations, 2006-2009., Extent: 0.18 cubic feet (1 box). (Box 38)
  The Public Relations series is housed in one box and is arranged chronologically. This series documents Secretary's involvement at official functions, as well as the planning, development, and carrying out of public relation activities or visits sponsored by the Secretariat. This series includes speeches or remarks, event programs or agendas, and background material.
  - 2006 Speaking Engagements (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - 2007 Commencements (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - 2007 Special Engagements (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - 2008 Speaking Engagements (Box 38, Folder 4)
  - 2008 Commencements (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - 2009 Speaking Engagements (Box 38, Folder 6)
  - 2009 Commencements (Box 38, Folder 7)
- VII. Legislative Files, 2007., Extent: 1.0 cubic feet (1 box). (Box 39)
  The Legislative Files series is housed in one boxes and is arranged by bill number. This series consists of legislation and supporting documentation affecting the Secretary of Education, as well as state agencies assigned to the Secretariat. Each file usually contains the text of each bill including any amendments, bill tracking information, and Legislative Action Summaries for the 2007 General Assembly session. A complete listing of all legislative files during the Kaine administration can be found in the Records of the Policy Office, Governor Timothy M. Kaine, 2003-2010 (bulk 2006-2009), Accession 44690 and 44701, State Records Collection, Library of Virginia (series III).
  The Virginia General Assembly's Legislative Information System contains searchable databases for bills and resolutions from 1994 to the present and reports to the general assembly. It also includes links to the Code of Virginia, Virginia Administrative Code, Constitution of Virginia, Charters, Authorities, Compacts and Uncodified Acts.
  - HB 1617-HB 3201; SB 744-SB 1419 2007. (Box 39)
- VIII. Special Projects and Governor's Initiatives, 2002-2010., Extent: 5.68 cubic feet (13 boxes). (Box 40-52)
  The Special Projects and Governor's Initiatives series is housed in 13 boxes and is arranged into six subseries. Subseries have been designated for: A. Virginia's P-16 Education Council, 2006-2009; B. Early Childhood Initiatives, 2002-2009; C. High School Reform Initiatives, 2002-2007; D. Achieve: American Diploma Project (ADP), 2007; E. Workforce Development, 2006-2010; and F. Teacher Quality, 2006. The series consists of agendas, agreements, briefing binders, correspondence, handouts, memorandum, notes, policies, presentations, and reports.
  - Subseries VIII.A. Virginia's P-16 Education Council, 2006-2009., Extent: 0.35 cubic feet (1 box).
    This subseries is housed in one box and is arranged chronologically. Governor Mark Warner's Executive Order 100 created Virginia's P-16 Education Council in October 2005. The Secretary of Education served as Chair. The Council's responsibilities included: identifying opportunities to better coordinate the state's education reform efforts from preschool to graduate school; serve as steering committee for oversight of the state's education reform activities as part of the National Governors Association (NGA) Honor States Grant; and develop approaches to improve transitions among levels of education. Governor Tim Kaine's Executive Order 40 issued in October 2006 continued the P-16 Education Council. The new order added an additional responsibility: work closely with the Start Strong Council and other entities to ensure that pre-K and early childhood initiatives are coordinated with other education initiatives.
    Many of the P-16 Council meeting files include handwritten notes probably written Kendall Tyree, Special Assistant to the Secretary of Education.
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2006 March 9. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2006 March 29. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - P-16 Working Group on Moving from Competence to Excellence: Readiness for Post secondary Education and Work Meeting, 2006 June 2. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2006 June 9. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2006 August 7. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2006 September 13. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting,. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2006 December 7. (Box 40, Folder 1)
    - P-16 Longitudinal Data System Work Group Meetings, 2006. (Box 40, Folder 2)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2007 March 1. (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2007 February 23. (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2007 May 17. (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2007 October 4. (Box 40, Folder 3)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2008 February 19. (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2008 June 24. (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2008 October 6. (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2009 October 6. (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - P-16 Education Council Meeting, 2009 December 8 (cancelled). (Box 40, Folder 4)
  - Subseries VIII.B. Early Childhood Initiatives, 2002-2009., Extent: 1.05 cubic feet (3 boxes).
    This subseries is housed in three boxes and contains records from Governor Mark Warner (2002-2006) and Governor Kaine. It appears to be a mix of files from Sarah Finley, Deputy Secretary of Education during the Warner Administration and Kendall Tyree, Special Assistant to the Secretary of Education during the Kaine administration. The original order has been maintained. This subseries includes agendas, meeting notes, correspondence, presentations, and reference material. Governor Kaine's early childhood initiatives included the Start Strong Council and the Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood Initiatives. On 16 January 2006, Governor Tim Kaine issued Executive Order 7 creating the Start Strong Council to develop expanded access to quality pre-kindergarten for Virginia's four-year olds. In July 2007, the Council completed its intensive study of pre-school opportunities for Virginia and presented six recommendations to Governor Kaine. The Council issued their final report in August 2007. Governor Kaine in December 2007 announced his voluntary program to gradually expand access to preschool for Virginia's four-year olds.
    Governor Kaine issued Executive Directive 3 on 10 August 2006 creating the Governor's Working Group on Early Childhood Initiatives. The Working Group, chaired by the Secretary of Education was responsible for coordinating the Governor's early childhood initiatives; served as primary link between Start Strong Council, Virginia Early Childhood Foundation, and existing early childhood programs within the executive branch; strengthen partnerships with state and local elected officials and non-profit and private sectors to build long-term commitment to early childhood education; and provide policy support to the Start Strong initiative. Governor Mark Warner's Pre-Kindergarten/Early Childhood initiative, part of Education for a Lifetime, provided a foundation for Governor's Kaine's programs.
    - Youth Matters (Richmond Chamber of Commerce), 2004 November 19. (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Robins Foundation, North Richmond Partnership for Families, 2004. (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - Square One, 2003. (Box 41, Folder 1)
    - The State of Preschool: 2004 State Preschool Yearbook, National Institute for Early Education Research (volume) (Box 41)
    - Kids Count, 2003. (Box 41, Folder 2)
    - Preschool - Quality Programs, undated. (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Southern Regional Education Board (SREB) Survey on High Quality Standards, 2002. (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 2003. (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Everybody's Children: Child Care as a Public Problem (book), by William T. Gormley, Jr., 1995. (Box 41)
    - The Future of Children: Caring for Infants and Toddlers, The David and Lucile Packard Foundation, Volume 11 - Number 1, Spring/Summer 2001. (Box 41)
    - No Time to Waste: Indicators of School Readiness, 2004 Data Book (Box 41)
    - Start Strong Council, Letters of Interest, 2006. (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - Start Strong Council Meeting, 2006 June 21. (Box 42, Folder 2)
    - Start Strong Council Meeting, 2006 July 19. (Box 42, Folder 3)
    - Start Strong Council Task Forces Meeting, 2006 September 6. (Box 42, Folder 4)
    - Start Strong Council Task Force Meetings, 2006 September 20. (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Start Strong Council Meeting, 2006 December 6. (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - Start Strong Council Meeting, 2007 March 21. (Box 42, Folder 5)
    - 101s: A Guide to Positive Discipline, 2004. (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - CED, Financing Public Preschool Programs: Current Practices and Future Possibilities, 2006 November. (Box 42, Folder 6)
    - Early Enrollment - Studies, undated. (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Pre[k]now - Governor's Proposals for FY 2006 and 2007, 2005-2006. (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Governor's Early Childhood Partnership Grants, 2006. (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Pre[k]now - Diverse Delivery, 2006 July. (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - Early Childhood Research Papers of Dr. Robert Pianta, 2003; 2005-2006. (Box 42, Folder 7)
    - California Proposition 82 - Preschool For All, 2005-2006. (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Early Learning Council, 2005-2006. (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Early Childhood Comprehensive Systems Project, 2006. (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Virginia Early Childhood Comprehensive Systems, National Governor Association (NGA) Grant, 2005-2006. (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Governor's Early Childhood Summit (NGA Grant), 2006. (Box 42, Folder 8)
    - Pre-K Letter to Virginia House Appropriations Committee, 2008 January 24. (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Smart Beginnings Letters, 2009 December 18. (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Early Childhood Foundation, 2005-2006. (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - School Readiness Begins at Birth: Healthy Families and CHIP Making a Difference, presentation on 2006 October 23. (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Virginia Early Childhood Advisory Council Meeting, 2009 December 7. (Box 43, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous Reports and Presentations, 2006. (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Reports, 2006. (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - GED/Early Childhood, 2006. (Box 43, Folder 5)
  - Subseries VIII.C. High School Reform Initiatives, 2002-2007., Extent: 0.88 cubic feet (3 boxes).